<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A plaine and briefe discovery of those two beasts that are written, Revel. 13 And to show what dishonour and disgrace the clergie bring against Christ and his glorious church in reading some part of the service-book. Againe I praise God I have shewed in briefe the true signification of Christ and his glorious church, with those holy ordinances that doe belong unto it. Gathered and directed by that grace God hath given to me James Hunt. All glory be to God on high.</title>
            <author>Hunt, James, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1643</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 35 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86899</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H3731</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E70_12</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R1261</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99859309</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99859309</idno>
            <idno type="VID">111383</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86899)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 111383)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 12:E70[12])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A plaine and briefe discovery of those two beasts that are written, Revel. 13 And to show what dishonour and disgrace the clergie bring against Christ and his glorious church in reading some part of the service-book. Againe I praise God I have shewed in briefe the true signification of Christ and his glorious church, with those holy ordinances that doe belong unto it. Gathered and directed by that grace God hath given to me James Hunt. All glory be to God on high.</title>
                  <author>Hunt, James, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for J.H.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1643.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Octob: 11th"; "London.".</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church of England. --  Book of common prayer --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:111383:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A plaine and briefe diſcovery of thoſe two beaſts that are written, <hi>Revel.</hi> 13.</p>
            <p>AND <hi>To ſhow what diſhonour and diſgrace the Clergie bring againſt Chriſt and his glorious Church in reading ſome part of the Service-Book.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Againe I praiſe God I have ſhewed in briefe the true ſignification of Chriſt and his glorious Church, with thoſe holy Ordinances that doe belong unto it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gathered and directed by that grace God hath give to me</hi> James Hunt.</p>
            <p>All glory be to God on high.</p>
            <p>Printed for J.H. 1643.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:111383:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:111383:2"/>
            <p>IT is written, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.13. <hi>All things that are reproved <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by the light.</hi> Now by that glorious light God hath given to me, I will ſhow you the ſignification of thoſe two beaſts that are written, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13. The firſt beaſt riſeth out of the ſea, which ſignifieth the Pope and all his Clergy, which have gathered to themſelves ſo many falſe doctrines, that the Spirit of God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pares it unto the deep and broad ſea. But the ſecond beaſt he com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth up out of the earth, which ſignifieth the Biſhops here in England and all their Clergy, which have gathered to themſelves ſo many falſe written books, that for their number they may be compared unto the ſtarres in the firmament, which falſe written books do a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and proceed from the devill, who is called the god of the earth, and by thoſe falſe written books the Biſhops and their Clergy have deceived all thoſe people that are as yet held under their power: but the people whom the Clergy have blinded, they cry out againſt me ſaying, who hath made thee a Judge or a Preacher. My anſwer is, God my glorious Father, and Chriſt Jeſus my redeemer: they have raiſed me up by the vertue and divine power of their Word, for to be a Judge and a Preacher, for to judge and divide betwixt truth and errour, light and darkneſſe: for I hope all that ſhall read this book they may underſtand from whence my judgment doth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe and proceed. Again it is ſaid, the ſecond beaſt he exerciſeth all the power of the firſt beaſt before him. Now I will prove, that the Pope and his Clergy, and the Biſhops and their Clergy, their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er not long ago was both as one. Firſt for the Pope, he hath made the people believe, that no man can be a true and ſound Preacher, but he muſt be brought up in the Univerſities, and ſo ſay, the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and their Clergy: but alas they are deceived upon both ſides: for God hath laid the Goſpell in ſuch a complete way, that if there be a myſtery or parable that ſpeaketh ſomthing dark in one place, a man may find two or three places for to prove and juſtifie what that dark myſtery ſignifieth, and that is the true and perfect way to open
<pb facs="tcp:111383:3"/>and unfold the myſteries of God to the true meaning and ſignifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and I praiſe God I can prove theſe things may be done with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the help of the Latin or Greek tongue; for I can prove it by plain truth of Scripture. Againe for the Pope, he will not allow that any man ſhall be a Preacher for to declare his mind to the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, but firſt he muſt be ſworne for to obſerve thoſe Canons and ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticles that the Pope or ſome of his Aſſignes ſhall ſet forth. The very ſame power did belong to the Biſhops here in England.</p>
            <p>Againe for the Pope, all Magiſtrates and Church-Wardens are ſworne for to uphold the Pope and his Clergy in their way, that if any man reprove them, for to ſay, their power or their doctrine is falſe: then the Magiſtrates caſt him into priſon, or els the Church-Wardens will complaine of him in the Spirituall Court: and when he comes there, if he do not play the hypocrite, and ſay he is ſorry for that he ſaid, and fee the Officers with money, he ſhall be caſt into priſon; if not, put to death. The very ſame power not long agoe did belong to the Biſhops and their Clergy here in <hi>England.</hi> Againe for the Pope, he and all his Clergy have deceived the people, in making the people believe that the old law is a rule of obedience for the people to be led and guided by, and ſo ſay the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops and all their Clergy. But they are deceived on both ſides in their judgment: for I can prove, the more they bring the people un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the obedience of the old Law, the more they bring them under the bondage of the devill. My firſt proofe is <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Foraſmuch then as the children were made partakers of fleſh and bloud, Chriſt like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe tooke part of the ſame, that through death he might deſtroy him that had the power of death, that is, the devill, and ſo to deliver all thoſe who through feare of death were all their life time ſubject to bondage.</hi> This place of Scripture doth plainly ſignifie, that all thoſe people that were under the old Law, they were under a yoke of bondage un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Chriſt freed them by his ſuffering on the croſſe. Again, <hi>Rom.</hi> 7.6. the Apoſtle ſaith plainly, and ſo ſay I, <hi>Now we are delivered from the Law, that being dead, wherein we were held as under the chaines and bondage of Satan, that we ſhould ſerve in newneſſe of ſpirit, and not in
<pb facs="tcp:111383:3"/>the oldneſſe of the letter: that is, in newneſſe of the Goſpell, and not in the oldneſſe of the law.</hi> Thus I have proved in briefe, that the old Law is the ſpirit of bondage, and ſo is the devill. And hereby I have over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thrown the Pope and his Clergy; and the Biſhops &amp; their Clergy in their judgment, becauſe they ſay, the old law is a rule of obedience. Againe, I will ſhew you in briefe, that S.<hi>Pauls</hi> falſe zeale was to the old Law when he was a perſecuter of Chriſt, for he ſaith plainly conſerning his zeal perſecuting the Church, <hi>Touching the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe that is in the Law, blameleſſe,</hi> Phil. 3. Thus I have proved in briefe, that S.<hi>Pauls</hi> falſe zeale was to the old Law when he was a perſecutor of the Church of Chriſt, and in ſo doing, let any man judge if he were not an enemy to God, and a friend unto the Devill; and ſo will all thoſe Divines be found and proved ſo to be, that keep the people under the obedience of the old Law. Againe, I ſay, all thoſe Magiſtrates and Church-wardens will be found to be Gods great enemies, that ſhall ſtrive to uphold the Clergy in their wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe; and thus I have proved in briefe, and ſhall prove againe at large, that thoſe two beaſts ſignifie the Pope and his Clergy, and the Biſhops here in England, and their Clergy, which by their falſe power as conſerning Church government, and falſe doctrine, they keepe the people under the bondage and captivity of the devill; and the plaine truth is, many of the Magiſtrates and Church-wardens doe yet uphold them in their abominable wickedneſſe, for they will not ſuffer the Prophets of God to reprove them for their falſe power, and their falſe doctrines, which is abominable in the ſight of our glorious God. My text ſaith, <hi>All things that are reproved are made manifeſt by the light,</hi> wherefore I ſay againe, by that glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous light God hath given to me, I will ſhew you in briefe what diſhonour &amp; diſgrace the Clergy bring againſt Chriſt and his glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Church, in reading of ſome part of the Service booke, for the Clergy ſay wee are all miſerable ſinners, and there is no health in us; now if there be no health in us, then wee are all repro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bates; for, <hi>Know yee not that Ieſus Chriſt is in yee except yee bee reprobates,</hi> 2 Cor. 13.5. Hereby I underſtand, that if Chriſt by the vertue of his word doth ſhine in his people, then I am ſure there is
<pb facs="tcp:111383:4"/>ſome health in us, but the Clergy ſay, there is no health in us: ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let any man judge if they do not accuſe the people to be in the ſtate of reprobation. Againe, the Clergy ſay, that we are all miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſinners: but if I ask any of them if the body of Chriſt be a body of ſin and miſery, they will anſwer no: Why then my anſwer to them again is in <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 1.22. <hi>God gave his ſon Chriſt to be head over all things to the Church, which is his body, the fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all.</hi> This place of Scripture doth prove and ſignifie, that all thoſe people that will be reconciled to Chriſt and to the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, their ſpirits ſhall be joyned to the glorious and myſticall body of Chriſt, and thereby they ſhall be ſet free from the bondage of ſin and miſery. Againe, the Clergy by reading of ſome part of the Service Book, they bring the people under the obedience of the old Law, which is the bondage of death and corruption Againe, the Clergy in reading of the Service Booke they teach the people to worſhip God in a falſe way, for they teach the people to fall downe on their knees, and pray for Chriſts Church militant here on earth, which is a vaine and falſe worſhip; for they have no Scripture in the new Teſtament to prove, that Chriſt hath any ſuch Church: but I can prove by plaine truth of Scripture, that Chriſt hath a glorious and triumphing Church here on earth: but that the Clergy teach the people to deny: for they ſay, that Chriſts Church is militant here on earth, but glorious and triumphing in the world to come, but not here upon earth. But I ſay plainly, that is a doctrine of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils: for the devill he ſtrives by his carnall miniſters for to teach the people to worſhip and obey that which is falſe, and to deny that which is juſt and true: for I will prove in briefe, that Chriſt hath a glorious and triumphing Church here on earth: for Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Joh.</hi> 12. <hi>Father glorifie thy name,</hi> then came a loud voice from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſaying, <hi>I have glorified it, and will glorifie it again:</hi> and <hi>Joh.</hi> 17. Chriſt ſaith plainly, <hi>The glory which thou gaveſt me I have given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, that they may be all one in us, that the world may believe that thou haſt ſent me.</hi> Againe, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.14. the Apoſtle ſaith expreſly. <hi>Now thanks be unto God, who alwayes cauſeth us to triumph in Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus:</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:111383:4"/>this word alwayes plainly ſignifieth here in this world, and in the world to come forever. Thus I praiſe God I have proved in briefe, that Chriſt hath a glorious and triumphing Church here on earth, and Chriſt will have his glorious and triumphing Church by degrees for to flouriſh over the face of the whole world, which will be to the overthrow of the devill and the falſe Church: and I praiſe God I have ſhewed you what diſhonour and diſgrace the Clergy bring againſt Chriſt and his Church in reading of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice Booke. My text ſaith, <hi>All things that are reproved are made ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſt by the light:</hi> now by that light God hath given unto me, I un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the Pope and his Clergy in their Service Book they have but the Lords Prayer and ſome of the holy Epiſtles of S.<hi>Paul,</hi> and other parts of the Goſpell, and thereby they have ſet a gloſſe and a glorious colour upon their Service Book, that ſo they may the more cloſely and craftily blinde and deceive the people, for it is ſaid in the 13. Verſe, that the beaſt maketh fire come down from heaven, and deceiveth them that dwell on the earth: I underſtand the fire that cometh out of heaven is thoſe parts of the Goſpell which the Pope and the Biſhops have cauſed to be put in their Service book: for the Word of God which is revealed in the New Teſtament doth ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie the Holy Ghoſt and fire. Againe I ſay plainly, that the divine power of the World of God in the Goſpell of Chriſt will be as a flaming and conſuming fire, for to burn up all thoſe errours and falſe traditions which the Pope and the Biſhops have invented in their Service book. Againe I ſay, that the divine power of the Word of God in the doctrine of the new Teſtament will be a flaming and a conſuming fire for to burne and conſume all falſe power, as touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Church government and falſe doctrines, which is contrary to the true worſhip and Word of God. Againe, I underſtand, that my glorious God hath appointed and commanded, that for preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and Church-government that muſt be held forth for to gather the people into the myſticall body of Chriſt. But for thoſe two beaſts, the Pope and his Clergy, and the Biſhops here in England, and their Clergy by their falſe doctrine and falſe power they keepe
<pb facs="tcp:111383:5"/>the people out of Chriſt, as I ſhall prove in briefe: for the Apoſtle ſaith expreſly, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.17. <hi>If any man be in Chriſt he is a new creature,</hi> and to be a new creature is to be reconciled to Chriſt, and to the new Teſtament. <hi>Old things are paſt away, behold all things are become new.</hi> I underſtand the old things that are paſt away is the old Law and Teſtament. For as circumciſion and the bloud of buls and goats did belong to the old Law and Teſtament, which Chriſt hath abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed. Now on the other ſide, Baptiſme and the Bread and Wine, they are two holy Ordinances which do belong to the body of Chriſt, and to the ſecond covenant of grace. Now theſe things which I have proved in briefe will overthrow the Biſhops and all their clergy: for their order is to read a chapter in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and then another in the new, and when they are in their pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, they joyn in their doctrine the old Law and Teſtament, and the new together, as if they were both as one: and in ſo doing they have blinded and deceived all thoſe people that are as yet held under their power: for if there be any Divine or other man that can finde any one place of Scripture in the new Teſtament for to prove, as he thinks, that the miniſtration of the old Law and Teſtament is to be joyned to the glorious body of Chriſt, if I cannot finde five other plaine truths to prove that he is deceived in his judgment, I will deſire no mercy, but I will be content to be put to death under the judgment of a Jury of twelve honeſt men: but what ſaith the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, <hi>Caſt out the bondwoman and her ſonne, for the ſonne of the bond-woman ſhall not be heire with the ſon of the free woman, Gal. 4.</hi> the ſonne of the bond-woman plainly ſignifieth the Devill and the old Law: for the old Law is the ſpirit of bondage, and ſo is the devill, as I in this book have plainly proved. Now I will ſhew you in brief of Gods love and mercy. For if the Pope and his Clergy, and the Biſhops and their Clergy will forſake the old Law, and their falſe power, and falſe doctrines and traditions, which is contrary to the true worſhip and will of God, and then be reconciled to Chriſt and the ſecond covenant of grace, God is rich in mercy to forgive them and receive them into his everlaſting kingdome of glory. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb facs="tcp:111383:5"/>I will conclude with S.<hi>Paul,</hi> as it is written 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.3. For this is good and acceptable in the ſight of God out Saviour, who will have all men to be ſaved and to come to the knowledge of the truth, for there is one God, and one Mediator betweene God and men, the man Chriſt Jeſus, who gave himſelfe ranſome for all to be teſtified in due time, whereunto I am ordained a Preacher, I ſay againe, whereunto God my glorious Father hath ordained me to be a Preacher, I ſpeake the truth in Chriſt and lye not, for the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God drawes but one way, that is to Chriſt, and to the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of the new Covenant, my text ſaith, All things that reproveth are made manifeſt by the light, Now by that light God hath given to me I ſhall reprove the Anabaptiſt, which will not allow young children to be baptized, but by the help of God I will prove in briefe by human reaſon, and ſpirituall ſignification of Scripture, that they are deceived in their judgement, my firſt proofe is <hi>Heb</hi> 10. For the Law having a ſhadow of good things to come, which doth ſignifie that the old Law was a type and ſhadow of the New, for the Apoſtle ſaith plainly concerning the Jews which were under the Old Law, he ſaith they were baptized to <hi>Moſes</hi> in the cloud, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.2. the cloud ſignifieth the Old Law, now I underſtand that <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi> did not baptiſe with water, but to ſignifie that circumciſion was a type of Baptiſme, and young children were circumciſed at eight dayes old. Againe, <hi>I</hi> finde it written <hi>Acts</hi> 16. concerning the Jaylor and <hi>Lydia,</hi> which were converted by S.<hi>Paul,</hi> it is ſaid they and all their houſhold were baptized.</p>
            <p>Now what man is able to gainſay but thoſe two perſons might have young children that were baptized by S.<hi>Paul:</hi> Againe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. when the Apoſtle told the Jews that they had crucified the Lord of life, they were pricked in their hearts, and ſaid, Men and brethren, what ſhall we do? <hi>Peter</hi> anſwered, Repent and be baptized, and ye ſhall receive the gift of the holy Ghoſt, for the promiſe is to you and to your children; theſe places of Scripture doth plainly ſignifie that all young children of faithfull parents are to be baptized to the myſticall body of Chriſt. Againe, Chriſt ſaid, Suffer little children
<pb facs="tcp:111383:6"/>to come to me, and forbid them not, for to ſuch belongeth the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of God: Marke this point I beſeech you, for Chriſt ſaith plainly, that the kingdome of God doth belong to young children, and Chriſt and his Goſpell ſignifie Chriſt and his Kingdome. Now if I aske the Anabaptiſts if they doe beleeve the Baptiſme with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to be an holy Ordinance, which doth belong to the body of Chriſt and to the ſecond Covenant of grace, they will anſwer, yea; why then my anſwer to them is in briefe, that all thoſe that will not ſuffer young children to be baptized, they doe exclude them from the myſticall body of Chriſt, and from the ſecond Covenant of grace; I pray God give all ſuch people grace to forſake that wicked practiſe, or elſe they will draw downe the fiery wrath of God upon their owne ſoules, and thus I praiſe God I have proved in briefe by humane reaſon, and by plaine ſignification of Scripture, that young children muſt be baptized. Againe, I have ſhewed you, that thoſe two beaſts doth ſignifie the Pope and his clergy, and the Biſhops and their Clergy, that their falſe power are both as one.</p>
            <p>It is written <hi>Iohn</hi> 16.13, 14. Chriſt ſaith plainly, When he the Spirit of truth is come he will guide you into all truth, he ſhall glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie me, for he ſhall receive of mine and ſhall ſhew it unto you, marke <hi>I</hi> beſeech you the commanding power of God, for Chriſt Jeſus who in the true and perfect God, he ſaith expreſly, that the ſpirit of truth ſhal receive of his, and ſhal ſhew it unto you: Now by that ſpirit of truth which Chriſt hath given unto me, <hi>I</hi> will ſhew you in briefe the true ſignification of Chriſt and his glorious Church with thoſe holy Ordinances which doth belong unto it, for there are three that beare record in heaven, the Father, the Word, and the holy Ghoſt, and theſe three are one, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.1. the Word ſignifieth Chriſt Jeſus who is the ſecond perſon in Trinity, and all thoſe people that will be reconciled to Chriſt and to the divine power of his word, their ſpirits ſhal be joyned to the glorious Trinity, my firſt proofe is in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 13.5. Examine your ſelves whether ye be in the faith, know you not that Chriſt Jeſus is in you, except yee bee reprobates: But how is Chriſt in his people? my anſwer is, by the vertue and divine
<pb facs="tcp:111383:6"/>power of his word which is revealed in his Goſpel. Again, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.19. What, know you not that your body is the temple of the holy Ghoſt which is in you. Againe, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4.4. There is one body, one ſpirit, one faith, one God and Father of all, who is above all, and through all, and in you all: Theſe three places of Scripture doth plainly prove and juſtifie, that all thoſe people that will be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to Chriſt, and to the obedience of his word, which is revealed in the New Teſtament, their ſpirits ſhall be joyned to the holy and glorious Trinity, Father, Son, and holy Ghoſt, which ſhall be all ingraffed as in one man, though they ſhall be in number thouſands of thouſands, and thus I praiſe God I have ſhewed you in briefe the true foundation of true and ſound Religion, which by the help of God I dare boldly ſay, that the Devill and all his carnall Miniſters ſhall never be able for to overthrow or ſhake this foundation. Now by the help of God I will ſhew you in briefe, how and after what manner children are to be baptized, for I think it fit that the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter firſt reade that portion of Scripture <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.21. For if there had beene a Law given that could have given life, verily righteouſneſſe ſhould have beene by the Law, but the Scripture hath concluded all under ſin, that the promiſe by the faith of Jeſus Chriſt might be given to them that beleeve, but before faith came, that is, before Chriſt came we were kept under the Law, ſhut up unto the faith which ſhould afterwards be revealed, which faith was revealed by Chriſt and the twelve Apoſtles, For ye are all the children of God by faith in Chriſt Jeſus, for as many of you as have beene baptized into Chriſt have put on Chriſt, and then after this Scripture is read, I think it fit for the Miniſter to reade the Lords Prayer, and then the Miniſter ſhall baptiſe the child, naming it by the name as the Father of the child, or ſome other in his ſtead ſhall give it, and ſhal ſprinckle water on the face of the child, ſaying, I baptiſe thee in the name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the holy Ghoſt, for a ſeale and pledge that for ever hereafter thou ſhalt not be aſhamed to fight un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the banner of the ſuffering of the Croſſe of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, but to continue his faithfull ſouldier even to thy lives end:
<pb facs="tcp:111383:7"/>So when the child is baptiſed with water, I think it fit for the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter to declare theſe words, ſaying, Chriſt ſo loved his Church and gave himſelfe for it, that he might preſent it to himſelfe a glorious Church, not having ſpot or wrinckle or any ſuch thing, but that it ſhould be holy and without blemiſh, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 5. that is, Chriſt wil have his Church which are baptized to his glorious body to bee ſo chaſt unto himſelfe and to his glorious Goſpel, that it ſhould be free from falſe doctrines and falſe worſhip which proceedeth from the devil, <hi>I</hi> doe not ſay that we ſhal be free from failings and infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities here in this world, for a child as ſoone as it is baptiſed it is joyned to the gloious body of Chriſt, but then God wil have them as they grow in ripeneſſe of yeares, that they ſhould be fed with the ſincere milke of the word in the doctrine of the New Teſtament, that they may grow thereby in heavenly wiſdome, from grace to grace and ſtrength to ſtrength, until wee all come into the unity of the faith, and of the knowledge of the Son of God unto a perfect man, to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fulneſſe of Chriſt, Epheſ. 4. that ye be no more children in underſtanding toſſed too and fro and carried about with every winde of doctrine and ſlight of men, and cunning craftineſſe whereby they lye in waite to deceive. but ſpeaking the truth in love, may grow up into him in all things which is the head even Chriſt, for God our glorious Father gave us his Son Chriſt to be head over all things to the Church which is his body, the fulneſſe of him that filleth all in all, unto whom be all praiſe, honour, power and glory both now and evermore world without end, Amen. Thus I praiſe God I have ſhewed you in briefe a true forme for the baptizing of children, which will be to the praiſe and glory of god, and to the edifying of the hearers, but for God-fathers and God-mothers, and the Croſſe on the forehead, be laid aſide. Now by the help of God I will ſhew you concerning the Sacrament of bread and wine, it is written 1 Cor. 11.28. But let a man examine himſelfe, and ſo let him eate of that bread and drink of that cup, for he that eateth and drinketh unworthily, eateth and
<pb facs="tcp:111383:7"/>drinketh damnation to himſelfe: And why doth he ſo? the anſwer is, becauſe he doth not diſcerne the Lords body: Now I underſtand as Circumciſion and thoſe Ordinances that are written, Heb. 9. did belong to the Old Law and Teſtament which Chriſt hath aboliſhed by his ſuffering, now on the other ſide, baptiſme and the bread and wine they are the holy Ordinances which doth belong to the my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticall body of Chriſt, and to the ſecond covenant of grace, for Chriſt ſaith plainly, Luke 22.20. This Cup is my blood in the New Teſtament which is ſhed for you: therefore I ſay againe, the Sacrament of bread and wine doth belong to the body of Chriſt, and to the New Teſtament, the Apoſtle ſaith, He that eateth and drinketh unworthily eateth and drinketh damnation to himſelfe, becauſe he doth not diſcerne the Lords body: Wherefore I pray God give the Biſhops and the Clergy all grace for to forſake the old Law and Teſtament which Chriſt hath redeemed us from, and that they may be reconciled to Chriſt and to the ſecond Covenant, which if they ſhall wifully refuſe to doe, they will be ſure to eate and drinke their owne damnation.</p>
            <p>Againe, if any man or woman have committed the ſin of theft or adultery, or any other hainous ſin, I pray God give all ſuch grace to forſake it by turning to Chriſt by true repentance, and then let them eat of that bread and drink of that cup, to their everlaſting joy and comfort: for Chriſt is the fountain of mercy and love, which doth not deſire that any ſhould periſh, but rather that all ſhould come to the knowledge of the truth and be ſaved: for the office of a Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is this. Firſt, he muſt ſhew the people how they muſt be ingrafted into the true vine. Chriſt, by the divine power of his Word, and then the people may grow in grace after they be ingrafted into the true vine: for as grace and vertue doe grow by degrees, by the divine power of the Word of Chriſt, that will be a means to cauſe ſin and wickedneſſe to die and vaniſh out of the people. Again, I think it fit that the Miniſter read the firſt chapter to the Epheſians and the Lords Prayer before he deliver the bread and Wine: and then the Miniſter ſhal deliver the bread, the people receiving it upon their knees, ſaying, take and eat this in remembrance that Chriſts body
<pb facs="tcp:111383:8"/>was crucified on the croſſe for to redeem your ſoul from the bon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage of hel and death, and honour and glorifie his bleſſed name for ever: and then the wine, ſaying, take and drink this in remembrance that Chriſts bloud was ſhed on the croſſe to redeem your ſoul from the bondage of death and hell, and honour and glorifie his bleſſed name for ever: and when the people have received the bread and wine, I think it fit for the people to ſing a Pſalme to the glory of God, and after that theſe words, The grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt &amp; the love of God the Father, and the moſt ſweet and comfortable fellowſhip of God the Holy Ghoſt bleſſe, keep and defend you from this time forth and evermore, Amen. Thus I praiſe God I have proved, that no people have any due or right to the holy Sacrament of bread and wine but ſuch as wil be reconciled to Chriſt and to the ſecond covenant of grace. Now I wil ſhew you in briefe for the marriage, for I think it fit that the man and woman take one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the hand, and ſay theſe words after the Miniſter, <hi>I John</hi> take <hi>Anne</hi> to my wedded<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> wife, to love and cheriſh in ſickneſſe and in health, until death us depart, according as God hath commanded, by the divine power of his Word, and thereunto <hi>I</hi> give thee my troth: and then for the woman, <hi>I Anne</hi> take <hi>John</hi> to my wedded husband, to love and to cheriſh in ſickneſſe and in health, until death us depart according as God hath commanded by the divine power of his Word, and thereunto <hi>I</hi> give thee my troth. And after this the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter ſhal read that part of Scripture as is written, <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. beginning at the 22. Verſe, and read to the end of the chapter. And thus <hi>I</hi> praiſe God <hi>I</hi> have ſhewed you in brief what wil be ſufficient for mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage, which is agreeable to Gods Word, and wil now for the burial of the dead: <hi>I</hi> think it fit that the dead bodie be caried into the Church, and there may be Divine Service or Preaching, for the edi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fying of the people, and then lay the dead body into the grave, and the Prieſt and people may ſing to the praiſe and glory of God the 113. Pſalme; for there is no cauſe of mourning for thoſe that die in the faith of Chriſt: therefore <hi>I</hi> ſay again, <hi>I</hi> thinke it fit when the dead body is laid in the grave for the Prieſt and people to ſing a Pſalme. And thus <hi>I</hi> have ſhewed you in briefe what wil be ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb facs="tcp:111383:8"/>for the burial of the dead. Now for Church-govemment, <hi>I</hi> think it fit for to have a Juſtice of Peace in every Pariſh of note for to bear the ſword of juſtice, for to puniſh the evil doers, and for the upholding of the juſt and good. Againe, <hi>I</hi> thinke it fit for to have Church-Wardens and Side-men in every Pariſh as already is, for to keep the Houſes of God in repair, and for gathering of money for the poore, that the hungry may be fed, and the naked may be cloathed, that ſo the members of Chriſt may rejoyce in glory together. Now ſome with ſay, this Church-government hath beene held here in <hi>England</hi> a long time. My anſwer is, in ſome reſpects it is very good: but by the help of God I ſhal prove in brief, that in ſome reſpects as it is held forth, it is abominable in the ſight of God: for the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates and Church-wardens they will ſuffer none to declare their mind to the people in the Churches, but thoſe which have beene brought up in the Univerſities, and in ſo doing they deny God of his divine power, for God breaths his Spirit where it pleaſeth him. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine I ſay, if God give a man a great and perfect gift concerning the art of preaching, the Clergy and Magiſtrates will not ſuffer him to exerciſe his gift unto the people which God doth allow and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand by the divine power of his Word, as I ſhall prove in briefe. My firſt proofe is in 1 <hi>Pet</hi> 2.9. <hi>Ye are a royall Prieſthood, an holy nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, that you ſhould ſhew forth the praiſe of him who hath called you out of darkneſſe into his marvellous light.</hi> Now <hi>I</hi> pray how ſhall the Saints and ſervants of Chriſt ſet forth thoſe praiſes, and honour, and glory which doth belong to Chriſt and his glorious Church: but by the manifeſtation of his Word which is revealed in his Goſpell. Againe the Apoſtle S <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith expreſly 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. <hi>When the Church are come together, let the Prophets ſpeak two or three, and let the other judge, for ye may all propheſie one by one, that all may learne, and all may be comforted.</hi> This ſaying of S.<hi>Paul</hi> doth plainly prove and ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie, that God hath appointed that every man ſhould have free liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty for to exerciſe his gift in the Church in an orderly and decent way, for he ſaith, <hi>All may propheſie one by one,</hi> and for to propheſie is to open and unfold the myſteries of God, to the true meaning and ſignification. Againe, I plainly underſtand, that prophecying and
<pb facs="tcp:111383:9"/>preaching, they are both as one in ſignification: for prophecying is to unfold the myſteries of God, to the praiſe and glory of his grace, and to the confounding of falſe power and falſe doctrine which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth from the devill, and preaching is for the very ſame purpoſe, I ſay that which doth proceed from God. Now the Apoſtle main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines his argument with a commanding power, for to prove that God doth allow that every man ſhould have free liberty to declare his mind in a decent way, for he ſaith expreſly in the 37. Verſe of the ſame Chapter, if any man think himſelfe to be a Prophet or ſpirituall, let him acknowledge that the things that I write unto you are the commandements of the Lord. Thus I praiſe God I have pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by plaine and cleer ſignification of Scripture, that God doth allow and command by the divine power of his Word, that his Saints and ſervants ſhould have free liberty for to declare their mind in the Church in an orderly and decent way, but the Clergy and Magiſtrates and Church-wardens, they will not ſuffer thoſe things to be done in the Church which God hath commanded by the divine power of his Word. I pray God give the Clergy and Magiſtrates and Church-wardens all grace to forſake that wicked practiſe, and that henceforth they will ſuffer thoſe things to be done in the Churches as God hath commanded, which if they ſhall wilfully refuſe to do, they will be ſure to have their portion in hell for ever. Thus I praiſe God I have ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed you in briefe how Church-government may be held to the praiſe and glory of God. Againe, I have ſhewed you how Church-government in ſome r<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects is held forth, which is abominable and hatefull in the ſight of God. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, I acknowledge the Lords Prayer, and other gol<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly prayers, and <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalmes ſhall abide in the Church of Chriſt for ever: for the Pſalmes, thoſe that are in proſe to be read for Divine ſervice, and thoſe that are in meeter for the people to ſing to the praiſe and glory of God; but for the old Law and Teſtament that is quite aboliſhed by Chriſt. Now if there be any Proteſtant, Papiſt, Anabaptiſt, or Browniſt, that can be able to ſhew and ſet forth Chriſt and his glorious Church, with thoſe holy Ordinances that doth belong unto it, in a plainer, and cleerer, and briefer way then I by Gods help have done, I ſhall rejoyce to ſee that man<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and I will be of his Religion, if it ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare ſo to be by the plaine and cleare truth of the word of God, and by the judgement of the high Court of Parliament, which I hope are gathered toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for the triall of the ſpirits.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
